So, I'd like to go through
some examples again here in the app.
For simplicity, I'll just use diagrams
that I painted in WS 2019/20,
so don't paint things live here now.
But we'll essentially talk through three variations
of how we might model such tree structures
(as seen here on the left) using classes
and ultimately the objects to go with them.
The goal will be that each of
these nodes of such a tree should
be an instance of somehow a class "Node".
And then the question is:
How can we represent the relationship
between objects, especially since it is
a tree structure (where here nodes
have such successors), by relationships between classes?
You can see a tree here on the left.
So nodes that have successors.
It is supposed to be a binary tree.
That is, nodes can have at most
two successors, as is the case here.
As usual in computer
science, the trees grow downwards.
And you can see here in each
case at the connections also the direction.
So this should be the direction
here: from parent node to child node.
Now we have here on the right a first
possibility how we could
formalize or model this.
So there should be this Node class.
It has an attribute.
That means, every object of this class
will have a whole number as value.
These are then exactly the numbers that can
be seen on the left in the tree.
And the parent-child relationship
corresponds to an association.
And this is a
self-association, so to speak.
That is, we have
this association here on the
right, where nodes are assigned to nodes.
And one thing that's
interesting is the roles.
So there's a father and a child, respectively,
at the parent and child ends of this association.
The arrowhead here
corresponds to the navigation
direction, so from where to where we go
(namely, from parent to child in the tree).
And the multiplicities we set according to
the character on the one hand that
each node can have at most one predecessor
node (the three has the two as predecessor node,
for example), but there are also nodes, namely
the root node, which has no predecessors at all.
Therefore, zero must
also be allowed here.
And in the other direction (in child
direction) every node has 0 to 2 successors.
Zero, because for example this leaf
node has no successors at all.
Maximum two, because for example
this node should have two successors,
and there should be
no more than two successors.
Therefore 0 to 2.
And 1 should also be allowed, because for
example the three here has only one successor.
It is interesting from the structural point of
view that such a self-association is quite allowed here.
When we drew diagrams with
the inheritance arrows last week,
there was exactly such a
situation that was not allowed.
That a class had
an inheritance arrow on itself.
Because that was inheritance.
For association, that's
not a contradiction.
Nodes can be associated to the same class.
It doesn't mean that in the
modeled tree, a node points to itself.
So that here is this association
from node to node in the class
diagram does not mean that
a node points to itself.
It means that a node can
point to one or more nodes.
By all means other nodes, that
is, other instances of the Node class.
That would be a first way to model here.
A second way would
be designed quite differently.
Namely, it would be due to the goal
that we might actually want to be
able to genuinely distinguish inner nodes (i.e.,
nodes of this type) from such
leaf nodes that have no successors.
Suppose we don't want
to have a class "Node"
that stands for every node in this tree.
Rather, we want to model the
inner nodes and the outer nodes separately.
Perhaps because we want them to
somehow perform different functionalities in addition.
In addition to the fact
that they carry a number.
Then we could have two different classes,
for leaf nodes and for inner nodes.
On the other hand, of course, they have something in
common, which is the fact that they carry this value.
So maybe it makes sense to have
that as two subclasses of a more general
class, which is for nodes (independent of
leaf or inner nodes; and which has this
attribute "value"), and from which the other
two more specific node classes then inherit.
If we implement this idea,
it might look like this.
It looks a bit more complicated
at first, but it is more precise.
What do we have here?
We have this Node class.
It is marked here as "abstract".
The background of that,
as it says down here,
is that then no instances can
be created of this class itself.
So there will be no
instances of this abstract class "Node".
That's just there to serve
as a superclass for these
two more specific classes
of inner and leaf nodes.
And those can be instantiated.
So every node that will ever exist
will be either inner node or leaf node.
Because you've marked
the superclass as abstract
and therefore no objects
can be formed from it.
So that's sort of
the function of this annotation.
Then the value attribute is
located here in this superclass.
Therefore it does not have to be
mentioned again with the leaf and inner nodes.
Because they then inherit
it via these two connections.
And then it is relevant that there is of
course no more self-association from inner nodes
to themselves, and from nodes to themselves.
Now it is that there are the leaf nodes.
Of course, they don't have children
(logically, because they are leaf nodes), therefore
no further association somehow leads away from there.
There is no such thing.
That exists only from the inner nodes.
Then here the situation looks
similar as before, with one difference:
There is no longer 0..2, but 1..2.
Why is that?
Because we now provide this
association only at inner nodes.
And they really have
at least one successor.
In the example before we
had to have 0..2 here,
because a node could also be a leaf
node and then have no successor at all.
Now that we say that the leaf nodes
are explicitly modeled as a class of their
own (and that they have no successors, we
can see from the fact that there is no
association), we can say again for the inner
nodes that they always have at least one successor.
That's why there is a 1 at the top.
Conversely, each node still
has zero to one predecessor.
Therefore here still stands 0..1.
And then it is still interesting
that this association of inner nodes does
not go back somehow to
inner nodes (is no self-association).
But it leads to nodes generally.
Which then means concretely
that the children of a
node can be leaf nodes
as well as inner nodes.
Because they both inherit from the abstract
class "Node" to which this child relation points.
So then that's another way,
a more sophisticated way of
describing the situation from the
slide before (this target situation).
And then yet another
variation (changed in a
different way) might be as follows.
Let's say we'd like to know
about the nodes and the links, respectively,
what the left and right successors are.
So instead of simply having the
connection as in this picture here,
we want to have written on it (or
expressed, recorded) what the
right and left successor are.
Then we can't just have one
association that somehow stands for successor.
But we must have separate
associations for left and right successors.
For example, it might look like this.
So we go back to a single Node class.
That carries a value as an
attribute, and then there are two associations:
one for left successor,
one for right successor.
Of course, the value is no longer
0..2, but 0..1, because there can be at
most one left and at most one right successor.
Vice versa, here again 0..1 is written,
because each node can also have at
most one predecessor, whose left successor it is.
We see here also:
Structurally in the class diagram, self-reference
is allowed, for example, but also,
for example, that there are two different
associations for the same classes "Node" and "Node".
Which was not allowed with
the inheritance arrows like this.
In fact:
The association arrows and
diagrams we build from them
have fewer structural constraints.
They can have cycles, for
example, or self-cycles, and multiple
associations between the same partners.
Unlike inheritance.
Now we could express something like that.
That's covered, there are just,
for example, these multiple nodes.
Here, explicitly, not only
the connection structure is
expressed, but also what each
left and right successor are.
Then there's this formulated question
of whether there's anything problematic here.
I had discussed that in
the past here as possibly
problematic about this modeling as
it is now designed here:
By splitting the child relationship into
left and right relationships, we suddenly
have the situation where
a node could have a
left predecessor as well
as a right predecessor.
What this modeling (as it
stands now) would allow is a
constellation like the following with
three nodes and the following association.
Namely that the node three would be left
successor of two and right successor of one.
And that would no
longer be a tree structure.
That would not have been possible with
this, as well as with this modeling.
Here that would have prevented this 0..1.
There is at most one
predecessor and not one predecessor whose
left, and one predecessor
whose right successor one is.
How can we remedy this?
With the means which we have treated
now, we cannot fix this at all.
The multiplicities simply
don't prevent that.
They just say:
One can now have a predecessor on
the left and one on the right.
You can't express that you can have one
on the left or one on the
right, but overall you could have only one.
Associations simply don't allow
us to express that.
We would need compositions for that because
they have more constraints on object instances.
We'll deal with that in a later
video, probably right in the next one actually.
Not on this example.
But what is special about
composition and goes beyond the constraints
expressed by multiplicities.